<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
        <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM "global.ent">
        %global_entities;
        ]>
<chapter xml:id="introduction" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <xi:include href="includes/author_azrzavy.xml"/>

    <para>
        Managing and operating on hierarchical data structures is an issue in many projects, alongside with security
        concerns, versioning and querying. Till now, neither open nor closed source projects or frameworks offer
        possibilities to dynamically define and manipulate the structure of hierarchical data in a scope like &flexive;.
        Hence the urge to provide a solution that combines flexibility, security and performance in one customizable
        package.
    </para>

    <para>
        &Flexive; is a JavaEE 5 open-source (LGPL) framework for the development of complex and evolving
        (web-)applications. It speeds up development as it handles numerous important application issues and keeps your
        application flexible over the development-cycle. It is based on the lastest industry-standards like EJB 3, JSF,
        etc.
    </para>

    <para>
        The &Flexive; backend application is an optional application built on top of the framework and is licensed under the
        GNU General Public License (GPL). It helps you to visually manage most aspects of &flexive; - like defining data structures,
        building queries, manage users and security, etc. 
    </para>

    <para>
        &Flexive; concentrates on enterprise-scale content storage and retrieval, and includes comprehensive JSF support
        for displaying and manipulating these contents in web applications. The runtime environment can be included in
        existing JavaEE applications, but you can also build new applications and package them into stand-alone JavaEE
        applications. Our emphasis lies on the runtime environment, so if you are looking e.g. for tool-driven JSF
        development, take a look at the popular JBoss Seam framework and embed the &flexive; runtime environment in that
        project.
    </para>

    <para>
        The goal of &flexive; is to relieve you from many tendious and repetitive programming tasks when building
        secure, data-centric (web-)applications.
    </para>

    <para>
        If you are new to &flexive; please use the following tools to get started:
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The &flexive;
                    <link href="http://www.flexive.org">website</link>
                    will provide you with top-level information about &flexive;. Have a look at
                    the "<link href="http://www.flexive.org/explore-flexive">Explore [fleXive]</link>" section.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    This reference documentation will provide all information to use &flexive; for the development of
                    your application.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    In the &flexive;
                    <link href="http://wiki.flexive.org">wiki</link>
                    you will find more tutorials, HowTo's, samples and developer infos
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link href="http://www.flexive.org/faq">FAQ</link>'s are anwered on the &flexive;
                    <link href="http://www.flexive.org">website</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        For questions, use the &flexive; forum and mailinglists. We also provide a issue trackings system for bug
        reports and feature requests. In case you are interested in the development of &flexive;, have a look at the
        Development Section on the &flexive; website and join the developer mailinglist.
    </para>

    <para>

        &Flexive; is a Professional Open Source project. UCS - unique computing solutions gmbh (<link
            href="http://www.ucs.at">http://www.ucs.at</link>) offers commercial development support and training
        for &flexive;.
    </para>

</chapter>